<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antiquity &amp; original of the Court of Chancery and authority of the lord chancellor of England being a branch of Serjeant Snagg's reading, upon the 28 chapter of Magna Charta, at the Middle Temple, in Lent, 13 Eliz. : with his congratulatory epistle, (by way of preface) to the Lord Chancellor Hatton, in 29 Eliz.</title>
            <author>Snagg, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4381A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875528</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875528</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152381</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93441)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152381)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2295:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antiquity &amp; original of the Court of Chancery and authority of the lord chancellor of England being a branch of Serjeant Snagg's reading, upon the 28 chapter of Magna Charta, at the Middle Temple, in Lent, 13 Eliz. : with his congratulatory epistle, (by way of preface) to the Lord Chancellor Hatton, in 29 Eliz.</title>
                  <author>Snagg, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Seile ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England. --  Court of Chancery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152381:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANTIQUITY &amp; ORIGINAL Of the COURT of CHANCERY, And AUTHORITY of the LORD CHANCELLOR OF <hi>ENGLAND</hi> BEING A Branch of Serjeant <hi>Snagg</hi>'s Reading, upon the 28 Chapter of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta,</hi> at the Middle Temple, in <hi>Lent,</hi> 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> WITH His Congratulatory Epiſtle, (by way of Preface) to the Lord CHANCELLOR <hi>Hatton,</hi> in 29 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Major haeredit as à Legibus, quam à paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus.</hi> 
               <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Seile</hi> over againſt Saint <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in Fleetſtreet, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dediation">
            <pb facs="tcp:152381:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152381:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lords Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for Cuſtody of the Great Seal of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat an eminent and a learn'd Profeſsor of the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> heretofore in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript preſented to an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Predeceſſor of your Lordſhips at his firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to that high place, Be
<pb facs="tcp:152381:3"/>pleaſed to give a Puiſnè leave to preſent in print unto your Lordſhips at your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtiture. A ſmall fragment, I confeſs: yet ſuch, I hope, as will appear neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of your approbation, nor improper for your Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and Protection; The ſubject-matter, as well of the Authors Epistle, as of his Readers obſervations, being a little Map and Modell of your Lordſhips great Office and Juriſdiction, and rarely
<pb facs="tcp:152381:3"/>to be found in our printed Authorities; which, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, may be the Reaſon, why that antient and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Judicatory hath lately met with ſuch great Envy and Oppoſition; Learning having no other Enemy but Ignorance, and moſt Men being naturally inclin'd to apprehend amiſſe of that they comprehend not; Though it will not be denied, but that any Court of Iuſtice in <hi>England</hi> may admit of
<pb facs="tcp:152381:4"/>Regulation. My Lords, I ſhall not ſay any thing for the Piece, it ſpeaks Reaſon, and can beſt ſpeak for it ſelf. I ſhall only crave your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> pardon for this great preſumption of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt humbly devoted, <hi>T. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152381:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Hatton</hi> Knight, Lord Chancellor of <hi>England, Robert Snagg</hi> an Apprentice of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Laws of that Realm, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all increaſe of Grace, Mercy, and Peace, Honour, and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this World, and perfect Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity in the World to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen (Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) it came to my courſe to Read in the Middle Temple, after I had there continued a Puiſnè full 20 years, and more, (for ſo they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152381:5"/>are called till they Read) and then I was to become an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice of the Common Law, and in my Reading to deliver to my Fellows of that Houſe, ſuch Notes as I had collected in the courſe of my Study, that I thought to be moſt profitable to be opened for the exerciſe and uſe of Law in our time; And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had looked into ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Travels that had Read before me, and other Writers, and found many ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, and ſundry Incertainties touching the Commencement of our Law, and whence it came, and what it was; and I thought it as meet (as <hi>Tully</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152381:5"/>teacheth) that it ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, <hi>Quid eſt de quo diſputetur,</hi> as to enter into argument of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular caſes which were to be decided thereby: which is the manner of that exerciſe, well known to your Lordſhip, as one that entred by that Gate into the happy and honourable Courſe of life, that God of his great Goodneſs hath moſt graciouſly led you in, from Grace to Grace, and Honor to Honor, to the higheſt Honor and moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Office that is in <hi>England</hi> under her Majeſty, who is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate in all Dignity, Honor, and Authority under God in this Land. But when I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152381:6"/>according to my capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of all the Reports that be in print of the practice of the Law, and of ſome other that I have, I could find no certainty of the Commencement of it, what it was, nor whence it came. For ſome ſaid, it was the Cuſtom of <hi>Normandy</hi> that the Conquerour brought in, and placed here; Some, that it came out of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> brought by thoſe people that were called <hi>Angli,</hi> that came hither to inhabit, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Land took the name of <hi>Angolia,</hi> and the Law the name of <hi>Lex Angliae,</hi> which ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more of Reaſon, that is the ground of our Law; And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152381:6"/>ſome imagined one thing, and ſome another; But that great learned Judge Mr. <hi>Littleton,</hi> in his firſt Book ſatisfied me, that it could neither be the Law of <hi>Normandy,</hi> nor of any other Country in <hi>Germany,</hi> nor elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, but peculiar to this Land; For he ſaith, <hi>That Tenant by the Courteſy of</hi> England <hi>is to hold the Land, if his Wife die, during his life, by the Law of</hi> England, <hi>&amp; is called Tenant by the Courteſy of</hi> England, for this, that this is not uſed in any other Realm, but only in <hi>England;</hi> whereof I collected, that if the ſame Law had been in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Realm, that Tenure by the Law had likewiſe been there.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152381:7"/>
            <p>And I found in ſtories, that preſently after the Conqueſt there were divers Inſurrections not only of the people, that did riſe without Reaſon, but of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Nobility of the beſt ſort, who endured Famin, (and that ſo far as they did ear the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt vermin) yea, and the utter overthrow of their Houſes and Poſterity; And all their cauſe was, but to be reſtored to their antient Laws &amp; Liberties. And that civil diſſention continued long for that cauſe, and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, without reſtitution of them, would not yield to their Kings, as men that ſhewed themſelves to be made of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152381:7"/>right <hi>Engliſh</hi> mould, ready to endure any pain and loſs, rather than the loſs of their native Laws &amp; Liberties, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject themſelves to the Will-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their new Lords, and new Laws, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror brought in, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and oftentimes the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures of their Kings, who did all, and took all, as pleaſed themſelves, under pretence of their Prerogative; which Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative rightly uſed, and truly underſtood, is a thing moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable to the Crown, and not prejudicial to the Law, nor hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Realm, nor any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects lawful Intereſt, or Liberty.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152381:8"/>
            <p>But that Will-government in the Kings, diſcontentment in the Nobility, &amp; continual Wars within the Realm, continued until K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. who (being by that time by divers deſcents purged and purified by our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Air, and by Education after the order of our Nation, and ſo become <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and of a better nature than the Aliens, and their offſpring) of love to his ſubjects, was content to allow <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws; And thereupon, the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>Febr.</hi> in the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his Reign, granted under his great Seal the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> thereby to reſtore the Laws of the Land, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152381:8"/>of the Subjects, and to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his Prerogatives, ſo, as they ſhould be prejudicial to neither.</p>
            <p>But after, kindled (as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) by the heat of his youth, he continued not in that good mind, but infringed the ſame <hi>Charter,</hi> and choſe his Will for his direction, (as others his late Predeceſſors had don) and left that Law of the Land, which he had granted to be Reſtored and Revived. Whereupon 40 years wars after that followed between him and his Barons, (as they be generally Termed, though the greateſt Earls, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the chief of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, were Partners therin) which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152381:9"/>were never fully appeaſed, until the Parliament was holden at <hi>Marlebridge</hi> about the 52 year of his Reign, when and where that <hi>Charter</hi> was enacted in that Parliament, and thereby the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Laws and Liberties revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and reſtored; which <hi>Charter</hi> ſo enacted, ſithence hath been by all Kings &amp; Queens ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſworn at their Coronations to be kept, and ſo hath been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credly Obſerved to this day, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome Forgetfulneſs in ſome Kings, and Ignorance in ſome Officers, hath infringed the ſame. But now, by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing plentifully powred upon us, it is in ſull Uſe, to the great
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152381:9"/>Comfort of all good Subjects, and immortal fame of her moſt Excellent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>And in the 28 Chapter of that <hi>Charter</hi> and Act of Parliament, I find it ſet down in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, in excellent and ſignificant brief words, to this effect, <hi>That no Freeman ſhall be dealt with either in Life, Liberty, Lands, Liberties, Body or Goods; nor that the King would ſend for any, nor proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any,</hi> Niſi per legale judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parium ſuorum, aut per le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem terrae; <hi>And that the King would not defer, deny, nor ſell Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or Right to any;</hi> which is, as it were, the ſum of all the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> &amp; Act, and the whole mark
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152381:10"/>that was ſhot at, to revive the antient Laws, and reſtore the antient Liberty and Liberties to the Subjects.</p>
            <p>Wherein I noted, That, both how far the Prerogative ſhould go, and what is Right and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice common to all, is referred to be decided <hi>per legem terrae;</hi> what therefore that <hi>Lex terrae</hi> was, which was ſo carefully ſought, &amp; dearly bought with ſo much Noble blood, which was then thereby revived, I thought if I could find, I had that I ſought for.</p>
            <p>And therfore I thought it beſt to begin with ſuch Reporters, or Writers of our Law, as writ
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152381:10"/>neareſt the time of that <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and looked into Mr. <hi>Bracton,</hi> that wrote about 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. the very time of the firſt granting of the <hi>Charter,</hi> who was one of the chief that were appointed (as it is delivered by Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to find out again the antient Laws of the Land, when the King was pleaſed to put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the force that they had loſt by the Conqueſt. And in his Book in print, I find it thus written, <hi>Cum autem ferè in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Regionibus utatur legibus, &amp; jure ſcripto, ſola Anglia uſa eſt in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is fmibus jure non ſcripto, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine; in ea quidem ex non ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, jus venit quod uſus comprobavit.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152381:11"/>And after that, he ſaith in the next Chapter theſe words, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Anglicanae fuerunt approbatae conſenſu utentium, &amp; Sacramento Regum confirmatae.</hi> And Cap. 3. <hi>Conſuetudo more utentium approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vicem Legis obtinet, &amp; conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis non vilis eſt authoritas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And he ſaith further, Lib. 1. Cap. 8. treating of that Law which he calleth the Cuſtom of the Land, <hi>Lex autem facit Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem; attribuat igitur Rex Legi, quod Lex attribuit ei, id eſt, dominatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; poteſtatem; nam ubi domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur voluntas, &amp; non Lex, ibi non eſt Rex.</hi> Whereof may be aptly collected, that before this Law was there was no King here in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152381:11"/>this Land; for if the Law of the Land made the King, there was none before it; But Kings we find by all Stories to be of a great antiquity here in this Land, and ſo by conſequence the Law muſt.</p>
            <p>And then looking for that matter in the Reports of the Law, I found a Book Caſe, in 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 18. That it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed by the Judges, that the Common Cuſtom of the Realm was the Law of the Land; And in that point look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further, I found all Books of Law agree; which Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Judges from time after the Enacting of that Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152381:12"/>and the judgement of Mr. <hi>Bracton</hi> before at the time of the penning of the <hi>Charter,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in one, ſatisfied me, That <hi>Lex terrae,</hi> which is there ſet down, and thereby revived, and now holden by the great <hi>Charter,</hi> whereto every King and Queen is ſworn at the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, was the antient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Land, that all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſeveral Nations that at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times inhabited here li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked beſt of, as fitteſt for this place, whereby the Kings lived in greateſt Honor and Eaſe, and the People in greateſt Quietnes and Freedom, wherfore there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings were content to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152381:12"/>bind themſelves, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects could abide no other. And ſo I drew that travel to this concluſion, That our Law is the antient Cuſtom of the Country or Land, and of that Antiquity, that there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord nor Matter that can ſhew the Commencement thereof, nor any man can tell it, but it was before all memory of Man that remaineth in the world, conſiſting of Maxims, General Grounds, &amp; Rules, received, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved &amp; allowed as juſt, good, &amp; neceſſary for the Governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this Land, begun when this Land firſt became a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth under a King, and ever
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152381:13"/>ſithence uſed, approved, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, from time to time, time out of mind of Man, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience found in all Ages to be fitteſt for the place, and to be neceſſary, honeſt and profitable both for the Prince and People, and being ſo found fit and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, it became a Cuſtom to be obſerved of all that ſhould inhabit, or remain here, and when it was loſt by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, it was again reſtored by Common conſent of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as was neceſſary it ſhould be; for that the force it had by Cuſtom and Uſage was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the Conqueſt; So as the Cuſtom of the Realm revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152381:13"/>by Parliament, is the Law of the Land, which is the <hi>Genus</hi> to all; And the Parliament and the Acts thereof, and the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of the Prince, and the particular Cuſtoms of ſeveral Counties, Cities, Boroughs, &amp; Manors, be all but <hi>Species</hi> of it: For that General Cuſtom of the Realm, which is the Law of the Land, authorizeth the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, limiteth the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, alloweth and diſalloweth of Private Cuſtoms, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in <hi>England</hi> is to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not to be allowed, as they are conſonant or diſſonant to the reaſon thereof.</p>
            <p>But when I had found out
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152381:14"/>this by Reading, then looking into the courſe of Practice, I found the Lord Chancellor fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting higheſt in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and had moſt to do, &amp; bare the greateſt rule; and yet gave his judgement (as it ſeem'd to me) as it pleaſed himſelf, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Law of the Land re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the caſe. And ſeeing Men of great Honor, Learning, &amp; Integrity ſit in that place, and ſo judge. I was in a maze, not finding at the firſt how it could ſtand with the <hi>Great Charter,</hi> that referred all judgement <hi>ad Legem terrae,</hi> and how any thing different from that Law could be allowable in the Land, ſith
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152381:14"/>the Kings were all ſworn to maintain the <hi>Charter</hi> that reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Law, and his Lordſhip and all the Judges were placed by the King.</p>
            <p>But when I looked further, and peruſed it well, I found, that the Cuſtom of the Land, which is that <hi>Lex terrae,</hi> allowed of that Authority alſo, as of the reſt; and that it was alſo a <hi>Species</hi> of that <hi>General,</hi> the Law of the Land, which was the ant ent Cuſtom of the Realm; And that it was of neceſsity to be in that ſort: For that the Common Law, Cuſtom of the Realm, or Law of the Land, (term it as they liſt) ſtanding of General
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152381:15"/>Grounds, Rules, and Maxims, it was impoſsible but ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſes muſt fall out, that either the General Rule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it lighteth ſhould be too bard for it, or too ſhort to reach it; And therefore was it of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity (to the end that all Caſes might be judged according to Right and Equity,) to have one under the Prince, above the reſt, to have ſuch an Authority that might judge <hi>ſecundum ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum, &amp; bonum, &amp; ſanam conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam,</hi> in theſe caſes, and to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate where the Rule of Law would light too hard, and to ſupply where it came too ſhort, and to the end that he might
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152381:15"/>have the ſending forth of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions to authoriſe Judges, &amp; of Precepts from the Prince to produce them to judgment that were to be ſued; And to be of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial Truſt with the King for keeping his <hi>Great Seal,</hi> &amp; ordering thereof, &amp; in ſuch other things as appertains to that office.</p>
            <p>Wherefore entring into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof, I found that Office alſo to be limited by the Law, and erected thereby; and therfore I gather'd divers Notes concerning the ſame, to Anſwer ſuch Objections as might in that reſpect be objected againſt that <hi>Charter</hi> and <hi>Statute,</hi> and the Law of the Land; which lying
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152381:16"/>by me when your Lordſhip was placed in that great Office, whom, I profeſs, I ever affected from my firſt comming to the <hi>Temple</hi> more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others (though then I knew, and was known of many of excellent Gifts and Natures;) And after your Honor was called to the Court by her Majeſty, I coming ſometimes to you from my old good Lord, &amp; dear Friend Sir <hi>Edward Saunders,</hi> late L. Chief Baron, I found you moſt gracious and favourable unto me, and now lately recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch honorable uſage from you, as I could not have deſired; when ſome of good and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Nature, &amp; excellent good
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152381:16"/>Diſpoſition dealt hardly with me, (as I thought) not affording me a good word, for a dutiful heart ever born them, and ſome hard pains performed for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; (which God, for ſome offence committed by me, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, laid on me,) yet your Lordſhip, of whom I had never deſerved any thing, nor ſhewed any Duty to, (except God revealed to you the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Affection of my heart) defended my poor credit (as <hi>I</hi> heard) to my great Comfort, and ſpake well of me.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to ſhew my ſelf thankfull, (for an ungratefull Man I have ever hated as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152381:17"/>and loathed as a Monſter) I bethought me how to preſent ſomething to your Honour, as a token of my dutifull mind, &amp; heart tyed to you; But amongſt things of price, I could find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was not too dear for me to compaſs, or too mean for you to receive, as a preſent, and that to deal that way, was but to pour water into the Sea, ſo plentifully (God be bleſſed for it) he hath bleſſed you with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance; And yet ſeeing your Honor had ſo well uſed me, for nothing, but of your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nature, I gathered hope, that you would accept ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, (were it never ſo ſmall)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152381:17"/>in good part at my hands, whoſe heart, and what he hath, is ever at your Commandement; And taking example by the poor Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diners, that preſent flowers to the greateſt Princes, that have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them but a ſmall ſmell, and no profit, &amp; yet are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of their gracious minds; I thought good to compoſe my Papers together that concerned the Authority &amp; Exerciſe of your Lordſhips Office, and to preſent them unto you; which, though too ſimple to inform your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of any underſtanding, yet at ſome vacant time may ſerve to recreate your ſelf in reading; as the plaineſt things, &amp; not the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt matters, are meeteſt for that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152381:18"/>purpoſe. But my good Lord, with theſe papers I preſent unto you my ſelf, &amp; my poor ſervice to be altogether at your Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, with faithful promiſe, That if my life may hold one of your fingers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurt, I will lay it down to help it, or to do you any good; &amp; while I live will ſpeak well of you to men, as one that deſerveth it of all. &amp; pray for you to God, that he may ſtill bleſs you with increaſe of his excellent Graces, much Honor, &amp; perfect aſſurance of everlaſting joy; And that her Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> and this Land may long enjoy you, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Laws and Liberties thereof, and the relief of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Subjects.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152381:18"/>
            <head>Notes touching the Office and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Lord Chancellor of <hi>England;</hi> Collected out of a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding made in the Middle Temple, in <hi>Lent, Anno Dom. 1570.</hi> upon the <hi>28</hi> Chap. of the Great Charter of <hi>England,</hi> granted under the Great Seal in the <hi>9th</hi> year, and Enacted and made a Statute at <hi>Marlbridge,</hi> in <hi>52</hi> year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Reader had found, That, by his Statute, <hi>No Man might be arreſted, impriſoned, or dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in his Perſon or Liberty, or put out
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152381:19"/>of his Freehold, Free Cuſtoms, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; Nor that the King would ſend forth againſt any, nor proceed upon any, but by the lawful trial of their Peers, or the Law of the Land; And that the King would not ſell, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr, or deny Juſtice or Right to any; And that that Law of the Land was the Antient cuſtom of the Country, which hath continued ever ſithence there was a King here, and that by it the King was made, and had his power and preheminence; And that it was confirmed by the Oath of Kings before the Statute, and ſworn to be obſerved by all the Kings ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence; And that all Judges are bound to try their doubts, and Judge their Cauſes accordingly, howſoever
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152381:19"/>their private knowledge, or Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence leadeth them;</hi> Then both by Practice, and by the Authority of Books, looking into the courſe of the proceedings in the Chancery, by the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> from time to time, it ſeemed as though that Office had been beſides the Law, erected out of the abſolute Authority that the Conquerors claimed; and that it hath been continued from time to time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law, and the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that <hi>Charter</hi> and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it were by a Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive above the Law; for that he is not tyed to any Form of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of any point of Fact that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152381:20"/>out doubtfull before him, as other Judges be, but may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine Witneſſes as he pleaſeth, and when he pleaſeth, to inform his Conſcience, &amp; alſo examine the parties by Oath or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and to proceed as it ſhall ſeem beſt to his Wiſdom, to beat out the Truth, as it ſeemeth good to him in his privat judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And that his Lordſhip may Order &amp; Decree the Cauſe, as it ſeemeth to him to agree moſt with Equity and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, howſoever the Law is in the Caſe; and to Impriſon the party if he will not be ruled by him, and forbear the benefit of Law, in every thing that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152381:20"/>Lord Chancellor thinketh to be Unconſcionable: So as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the firſt object, for that his Lordſhip is neither bound to the trial, nor the judgement that the Statute appointeth to be obſerved (as it ſeemed) upon the Letter, that his Authority is above Law, or beſides Law, &amp; ſo the <hi>Great Charter</hi> of <hi>England</hi> no further holden than it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Alſo it appeared by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, That no Man hath Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to judge according to the Law, before he hath ſome Grant or Commiſſion from the King or Queen out of the Lord Chancellors Office, under the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152381:21"/>
               <hi>Great Seal</hi> that is in his keeping: And alſo by courſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law (ſaving ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar preſcriptions in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Courts) the Judges can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold plea in any Cauſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til his Lordſhip ſend them it by an Original Writ framed in the Chancery, retornable before the Judges by his Lordſhips ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
            <p>But when it was well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, That the <hi>Charter</hi> and <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was, that none of theſe things ſhould be done, but according to the Law of the Land; And that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very King was ſworn to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, and that the Lord
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152381:21"/>Chancellor is appointed by the King to his Office; It was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that the Law of the Land appointed theſe things to be thus done by his Lordſhip, for ſome neceſſary cauſes known to them that firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the Law, and ſo that great Office, and the <hi>Great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the Law of the Land might all ſtand together.</p>
            <p>Wherefore then was ſought for, when that great Office of Chancery was erected, by whom, and for what cauſe? and it was found to be erected by the Inſtitutors of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, as a Member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of neceſsity to obſerve order
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152381:22"/>in making of Judges, direction of Sutes, and to relieve and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in thoſe Caſes, where the Judges by the general Grounds and Rules of Law, could not give competent Remedy by Law, according to Conſcience and Equity, as ſhall hereafter be more plainly ſhewed; And ſo his Lordſhip, nor his Office, no derogation to the Law of the Land; but his Office a member, and he a Judge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, without whom the Law could not have the perfection, order, and due honour that it hath; For the better perceiving whereof, it was Noted,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that thoſe (the Kings,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152381:22"/>Nobles, and Commons, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and whenſoever they were) that Inſtituted the Law of the Land, did ſee that it was beſt to make it ſo, as it might ſtand of General Grounds and Rules, that might comprehend all particular Caſes that ſhould fall out, and to bind all that were in one Caſe, to one judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or other Circumſtances; or elſe the Law could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Judges, how they ſhould proceed in judgement: For if conſideration of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or other circumſtance, might have given a ſcope to the Judges, to judge by one Rule,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152381:23"/>one Caſe one way, and another another way, the Judge might have made of the Golden Rule of the Law, a Leaden Rule, to bend at his will, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion would have followed, and infinite inconveniences; for avoiding whereof, they made the Rules to reach all perſons alike, according to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which regardeth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of no Man in judgement.</p>
            <p>Then, they did ſee, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would be over-reached; for ſome were too ſimple, and would truſt untruſty perſons, and be circumvented and were meet therefore to be holpen; Some would fall into the laſh
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152381:23"/>of the Law ignorantly, and therefore not to be puniſhed as thoſe that offended of Malice; Many might craftily over reach their Neighbours, by getting the better end of the ſtaff; And ſome by ſtrength bear them down, if by ſome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Authority the weaker were not upholden, and the ſimple provided for, and the ſubtill prevented. For in many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes men might offend &amp; wrong their Neighbours in ſubtil ſort, and be wronged by hap, or ſimplicity, or ignorance, and yet the General Rule of the Law could not fully reach or relieve them, that were ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reached
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152381:24"/>or circumvented.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Inſtitutors of the Law found it to be a thing of neceſsity, to tie the Judges to follow the Law in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all Caſes generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as the Caſe required: and yet to conſtitute one Supreme Judge further truſted than the reſt, that might have an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity abſolute and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ſupply and reform thoſe particular Caſes, that might happen as aforeſaid, according to Equity and good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to bind the parties not to follow Law, where by Law they might get more by ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or the others ſimplicity,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152381:24"/>than Conſcience would.</p>
            <p>Here grew an Objection, That it was a diſhonour to the Law to have theſe wants, by this great Man to be thus ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed; for that it ſhewd, that ſhe had not ſufficiency and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in her Grounds and Rules.</p>
            <p>But this is nothing, For there is no Law in any Nation, but particular miſchiefs have grown upon it; nor ever any Art or Science hath been ſo exquiſitely ſet down, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable Queſtions have been found in it. And that it cannot be otherwiſe, one example may ſerve; <hi>Moyſes</hi> that was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152381:25"/>the Law-giver to Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and delivered it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Inſpiration, was at the wall, we ſee, in his own Books, in divers Caſes that happened, both in the Political Law, who ſhould inherit, and the Ceremonial Law, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uncleaneſſe that came by touching a dead body; and he was driven to refer it to God to be decided, and could not decide it himſelf by the general Rule of the moſt perfect Law that ever was given to any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Then if <hi>Moyſes</hi> that man of God found ſome doubts that he could not decide, in that Law delivered by himſelf;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152381:25"/>Good Judges and learned may find ſome Caſes, that by Law they can hardly find a good proviſion for, but leave it to ſuch as God ſhall appoint to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Will by in Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſith by Law they are not otherwiſe provided for.</p>
            <p>Then it was Noted whereof his Lordſhip hath his name of <hi>Dominus Cancellarius Angliae,</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England;</hi> wherein all agree, that he is called <hi>Cancellarius, à Cancellando.</hi> But what he may Cancell, whereby he had that honour, hath been doubted. Some have ſaid, that he had authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Cancellare iniquam Legem Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munem,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152381:26"/>&amp; judicare ſecundum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam.</hi> But that hath no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and was rejected; for it is abſurd, that ſith the Law hath made him a Judge of Law, and his Office a member of the Law, and made thereby, (as as ſhall be plainly proved) that the Law ſhould give Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to deface or Cancell her ſelf, or that his Honour ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face that wherby he ſitteth, and hath his Authority. And to that end was cited Mr. <hi>Bractons</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Lex facit Regem, attribuat igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Rex Legi, quod Lex attribuitei, id eſt, dominationem &amp; poteſtatem;</hi> And thereupon it was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>à fortiore,</hi> If the King, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152381:26"/>hath an Authority by Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative above the Law in many caſes, as to pardon and acquit by Mercy, where the Law of Juſtice condemneth, muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the Law Dominion and Power: the Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, though he hath an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity beſides Law, and yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Law, is to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute Dominion and Power to the Law in all that he can, for that it made him an Officer in ſo high degree, and therefore he may not Cancell or deface it. Which point, that he is made by Law, and hath his Authority therby, is afterwards fully proved. And it is to be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152381:27"/>Noted, That his Lordſhip by his Abſolute power cannot ſtay the Courſe of Law, but onely bindeth the perſon not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Law in any Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable Courſe. This may ſerve to ſhew, that it was not ſaid of Cancelling the Law; for in thoſe Caſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it is found by experience, that the Law will take her courſe if the party call upon it, though the Lord Chancellor hath otherwiſe ordered the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But his Lordſhip hath his Name of Cancelling the Kings Letters Patents, which is a thing of as great Honour to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152381:27"/>his Lordſhip and the Law, as th'other had been of Diſhonor, and Diſgrace to both; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was Noted, That the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents of the Prince once paſſed the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> do bind both his or her Majeſty, their Heirs and Succeſſors, and all Subjects, yea ſo far, as the King or Queen cannot call them in, if they find them unfit, nor any Subject can gainſay them, if they be not juſt. Yet by Law if Letters Patents be paſt the <hi>Great Seal</hi> in deceipt of the King or Queen, the Judges by the Law are to adjudge it undue, and not to bind the King or Queen in that reſpect, wherein
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152381:28"/>they were deceived; but yet they muſt leave it under Seal, and cannot deface it. But if any Letters Patents paſs the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> injurious to any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or prejudicial to the Law, the Lord Chancellor as a Judge of Law, (and not by his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Authority) by his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary power, and by the courſe of the Common Law is to judge of it which proveth that the Law, and not Prerogative giveth him that power. For he is to hold plea of it by courſe of Law, and to call the party in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in it by proceſs of Law, and ſo proceed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law, and repeal it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152381:28"/>by Judgement, if it be found in Law to be injurious. And then the Lord Chancellor may Cancell it, and pull the Seal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, and deface it; which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King or Queen by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, nor any other Judge of Law, nor other Lord of <hi>England</hi> can do, but himſelf, who only hath that Authority. Wherefore, thereof he is called <hi>Dominus Cancellarius Angliae,</hi> as if it were ſaid, that Lord that only hath Authority in <hi>England</hi> to Cancell the Letters Patents of the Kings, that bind both the King and the Subjects, if they be injurious to any Subject, or prejudicial to the Law.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152381:29"/>
            <p>In this part, there were Three things Noted; One, that hereof his Lordſhip took his Name. Another, that this was his higheſt Authority, for that none but he had the like in the Land. The third, that his Lordſhip hath it given him by the Law, and is in that reſpect a Judge of the Law, and proceedeth in courſe of Law, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Conſcience, and by his Abſolute power, or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Authority; for he cannot judge thereof any otherwiſe, but by the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Then was Noted, As all juſtice floweth from the King or Queen, as from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152381:29"/>and no Authority or Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in <hi>England</hi> is lawfull, that is not drawn from thence; ſo is his Lordſhip and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, next under the King or Queen, to direct ſuch Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Grants as ſhall give Judicial authority to any judge according to the Law, which muſt paſs under the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> or they be not ſufficient. For example, There is no Judge made by Writ or Commiſſion, but it cometh from thence, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath any Man power <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere placita,</hi> but it muſt grow firſt by Grant from thence, except it be the petit Sutes, that belong to petit Courts, as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152381:30"/>Courts Baron, and County-Courts; whereof it is ſaid by Law, <hi>de minimis non curat Lex,</hi> but the Law left them to the Lords at home, to order them for the Peoples eaſe; Yet in theſe Courts if any falle Judgement be given, it cannot be redreſſed but by Writ out of the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to bring it before better Judges. But here of was noted, That though he muſt direct out all Commiſsions, and Grants, before any can have Authority to judge according to the Law, that his Lordſhip doth that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the Law of the Land; And the Commiſsions and Grants made by him are to be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152381:30"/>adjudged by the Law of the Land for their validity or inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity; And therefore that his Lordſhip therein is a Judge and member of the Law to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point and direct the reſt in that behalf, and is to do it in that form, and to that effect that the Law hath preſcribed him, which his Lordſhip may not alter; whereby it is apparent that he hath that Authority al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Then was Noted, That by the Common Law, if any would complain of wrong, or ſue for right, he was to come into the Chancery, and ſet down by one of the Clerks
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152381:31"/>thereof, a Brief of his matter that he would put in Sute, and that was by the Clerk to be ſet down in form in parchment, and a Precept written before it in the Kings or Queens Name, and that directed to the Sheriff of that Shire where the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff allegeth the Defendant was to be beſt found, or the cauſe moſt aptly lay to be ſued to Trial; which Precept Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth the Defendant or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to render right to the Plaintiff or Demandant, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the day prefixed in the Court appointed to him, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him to the Law, and that Brief encloſed in Wax ſealed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152381:31"/>with the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> the L. Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor is to ſend out by the courſe of the Common Law before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Subject can be ſued for any matter of weight, by the courſe of the Common Law. And that Writ is called in <hi>Latine Breve;</hi> wherein alſo was noted, a great regard that the Law had, that Men ſhould not be lightly heard to complain of their Neighbours, nor any Subject drawn into Sutes, nor troubled, nor any Cauſes (but the petit ones aforeſaid) ſhould be brought to judgement, but by his Honours direction; ſo as Judges ſhould not ſend for whom they would, nor liſten
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152381:32"/>to all that complained, but to do Juſtice to thoſe that were ſent to them by the Kings Writ, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Lord Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> to be Retorned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as fit to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, and meet to be drawn into Sute and Judgement. Though ſithence by uſage, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Courts have obtained o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceedings, by other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, according to their Courſe, and not by Originals, and that is not derogatory either to the Law, or that great Office; for ſome have grown by Grant, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Kings Prerogative, which both the Law and the Chancery alloweth, and are to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152381:32"/>allow of right, ſo it be not in derogation of their Authorities, and may ſtand with the Law of the Land. For the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> proceedeth by Bill, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Original, againſt ſuch as be Priſoners to the <hi>Mareſchal</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that juſtly; for that no Law can preſcribe the King a form to proceed in Iuſtice for thoſe Cauſes that be before himſelf, but he may receive any complaint, without Writ, and proceed as it pleaſe him, ſo he obſerve the Law for Iuſtice &amp; Iudgement, which is done there, as well as in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas, where all come in by Original Writ; For though
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152381:33"/>it be not by like form for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, yet it is by the ſame form of pleading and judgement, &amp; in matter &amp; ſubſtance of Law all one. And in this part it is manifeſt, that this Authority alſo in the Lord Chancellor to direct out Original Writs, is by the Law of the Land given unto him, and his form preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to him by the Law how he ſhould make them. And to that purpoſe there is a Book of Law left in the Chancery that the Chancery men are bound to follow, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Regiſter;</hi> And if the Writs be not made according to the form of Law thereby
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152381:33"/>preſcribed, the Judges will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them, and judge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> void; which is called in Law, aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Writ. So as it is apparent, that in this alſo his Lordſhip and his Office is by the Common Law, and are members of the Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Law. and that he doth it not by any other Authority above Law, or beſides it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Then was conſidered of his Lordſhips authority to judge, which appeareth in 9 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>fol.</hi> 14. in a Book-caſe, to be of two ſorts, or by two powers, <hi>viz.</hi> One according to the courſe of the Common Law, or Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law, which is there ſaid
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152381:34"/>to be <hi>Potentia ordinata,</hi> which is in proceſs, in pleading, and in judgement, according to the courſe of the Common Law of the Land; The other is ſaid <hi>Abſoluta potentia,</hi> which is in proceſs according to the Law of Nature, to ſend for the party to Anſwer, and receive his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer if he will make it, &amp; then proceed to examine the truth of the matter, and if he will not anſwer, but be <hi>Contumax,</hi> yet his Honour is to proceed to the examination of the truth, and not to condemn him in the cauſe for his obſtinacy, if it may appear that the matter be not good againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152381:34"/>
            <p>And there is noted this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which is apparent and common in practice, That where the proceeding is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Ordinary power, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleading on either part may marr his Matter, and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be according to the Law, howſoever the equity of the Caſe ſhall fall out: But if the proceeding be according to Abſolute power, though the party miſ-plead, if the Lord Chancellor ſhall perceive the matter to be good on his ſide, his Lordſhip is to judge for him for whom Equity ſerveth, be it the Plaintiff or Defendant, for that he is to judge as he ſhall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152381:35"/>find the matter to be in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence good or bad, and not as he ſhall find the pleading to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and good, or vicious and evil, or as the Law will in the Caſe. As for example, in ſuch actions as be brought in the Chancery before the <hi>L.</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, as an <hi>Audita querela</hi> to avoid a Recogniſance for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, or other good Cauſe in Law; And in actions brought according to the courſe of the Law, either by any of the Court, or againſt any of them by reaſon of their Privilege, and in Vouchers upon Aid-prayer of the King, and ſuch other, whatſoever actions are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152381:35"/>purſued there according to the courſe of the Law, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is not to regard what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would in the Caſe, but is tyed to the ſtrict courſe of Law, ſo as if the matter be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conſcience in his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips opinion, yet he is to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge with him that the Law ſerveth for, yea if his matter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be good, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel have loſt it by pleading, his Lordſhip can not help it in judgement; nor if the Law be againſt him, though Equity &amp; Conſcience would ſeem for him. But on the other ſide, if the proceeding be by the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power, howſoever the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152381:36"/>party or his Counſel overſee, or ſet forth their matter, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the preciſe Rule of Law requireth, if his Lordſhip per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by his Wiſdom that the cauſe in Conſcience is good on his ſide, his Lordſhip is to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge with him; for that then judgement is to proceed <hi>ſecundum Conſcientiam &amp; Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> and not in <hi>Forma Juris.</hi> But in any Caſe that is there in form of Law, if it fall out that in Conſcience it ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, the party may put in a Bill, &amp; follow it in that courſe, and then his Lordſhip may ſtay the courſe of Law.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Then was it enquired,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152381:36"/>Whether his Lordſhip may take order in all cauſes which are againſt Conſcience, or that the Law hath limited them alſo, and allowed of ſome to hold in that courſe, and ſome not? And it ſeemed, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience whereby his Lordſhip is to judge, is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> and to be <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Conſcientia,</hi> but <hi>Regulata Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia,</hi> and therein to follow Order and Courſe accuſtomed; <hi>viz.</hi> to take order in ſuch Caſes as by the Courſe of the Court hath been ordered before-time, and in Cauſes of like Equity, or greater; wherfore oftentimes Preſidents are ſought for and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152381:37"/>required, and for lack of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, it hath been ſought how caſes in the like reaſon, or in <hi>eodem reſpectu,</hi> with that that is then in queſtion, have been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to prove that that Court may take cognizance of the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>As for example, it is againſt Conſcience, that a rich Father ſhould ſuffer an honeſt Son to begg, &amp; that a rich Son ſhould ſuffer a good Father to want; yet his Lordſhip in thoſe caſes, cannot make the one to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his goods to relieve the other, according to Conſcience; But that, which that <hi>Regulata Conſcientia</hi> relieveth, is not when
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152381:37"/>one keepeth his own uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably, but when one ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an other mans Goods or Lands, or to trouble his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon unconſcionably; either by colour of Law, or extorted power, further or otherwiſe than in good Conſcience it ought to be; then his Lordſhip proceeding according to the courſe of that Court, is in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to relieve the party that is ſo dealt with, or his Lands or Goods ſo taken or ſought, contrary to Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And it was thought, that if it be unconſcionable that is done, if the Law in ordinary courſe may give a competent
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152381:38"/>remedy, and the party ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently able to follow it, and that there be no defect in any circumſtance, but that by the Law the party wronged may be relieved; that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ought not to deal in it, but referr it to the Law to be judged. But therein there is no certain Rule but his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips own Wiſdom, and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to diſcern whether the Law can relieve it, or not, or that there be any defect or not; ſo as if his Lordſhip think there is cauſe to retain it, he may, or diſmiſs it if it pleaſe him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is in that behalf
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152381:38"/>to direct him, as God ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And ſome caſes there be that ſeem unconſcionable, and yet the Law alloweth them for good and neceſſary, and never Lord Chancellor thought good to deal in them. As for example, That the Warranty of a Collateral Anceſtor that never had any thing in the Land deſcended upon one that had right, ſhould barr the right Owner from his Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, for that he is Heir to him that made the Warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though he hath nothing for it. Or that a ſuppoſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery in value in a Common
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152381:39"/>Recovery againſt a Cryer of the Court of <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> that is not worth a Groat, nor like ever to be able to make Recompence in value, ſhould ſtand for a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and be a barr of a mans lawfull Inheritance, and to barr him that he can never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it, ſeemeth in every Mans particular Conſcience to be unconſcionable; And yet the Law hath allowed of them, upon this General Rule of Law, Better to ſuffer a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chif than an Inconvenience, and upon the regard that the Law hath to ſettle Poſſeſſions of Inheritace in certainty, by
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152381:39"/>ſuch Inſtruments and Policies as the Law hath allowed to aſſure them by, of which kind theſe be; wherefore the Law hath not ſuffered them either by Law, or in Conſcience, at any time to be violated or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed, for any reſpect, or in any caſe.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And it was ſaid, That whereſoever an Act of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath made any proviſion for any unconſcionable thing that was not to be relieved by the Common Law, if the Lord Chancellor think in his Conſcience that the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath not ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the party, yet his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152381:40"/>is not to relieve him further than the Parlament hath done, as before the Act he might have done; for that ſo much is provided for, as the whole Three Eſtates thought meet, to whoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Lordſhip is to yeeld. But if any go about to defraud any Act of Parlament, or not able to ſeek relief as the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute appointeth, Then, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, according to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience his Lordſhip is to deal therein, when and where, as God and his Conſcience is to direct, and no other, nor other rule there can be for his direction in that behalf.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:152381:40"/>
            <p>Hereupon was it alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, That his Lordſhips Authorities Judicial, both by Ordinary power, and by Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power are limited by the Law of the Land; For in the Ordinary, he is tyed to the ſtrict courſe of the Law, as other Judges be; and in the Abſolute power, though not tyed to the courſe of the Law, yet he is to deal, <hi>per Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Conſcientiam,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of the Court; and in ſuch Caſes, as in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Conſcience and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty likewiſe hath been relieved before-time, but not in any Caſe that Law hath allowed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152381:41"/>of for good and neceſſary, nor in any that any Parlament hath made proviſion for, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for ſome circumſtances the party can not have that which the true intent of the Law, or the Parlament al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, but by means of that Court; And many things that a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would will a man to doe in Charity to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, his Lordſhip by his Conſcience cannot compell him to do, by the courſe of that Court.</p>
            <p n="10">10. But in all that Diſcourſe none could find how farr his Lordſhips Abſolute power
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152381:41"/>went, nor within what limits certain it could be contained, nor by what means he might find out the truth; But that is without limitation referred to his own Gifts, and the Grace of God, that giveth Wiſdom to find out the Truth, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to judge accordingly; ſometime to find it out by the Law of Nature, as <hi>Solomon</hi> did, when no Teſtimony could be found in the world, yet he found by her bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion the true mother of the Child; And ſometime it is found out by one mean, and ſometime by another: But God never faileth to give
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152381:42"/>wiſdom and means to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thoſe Offices and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that his Majeſty placeth men in; ſo as they ſerve him in Fear, and walk before him with a good Conſcience, and ſeek it in Humility, and with prayer at his hands, whoſe Will, which is Infinite, is the Rule of the Lord Chancellors Conſcience, and therefore his Authority in that reſpect is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and not limited in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Upon all theſe Notes the Reader concluded with this Note, That it is certain that his Lordſhips Office and Authority is by the Law of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152381:42"/>Land, and not derogatory thereto, but was conſtituted by the Law-makers to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply thoſe things that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that be bound to the general Rules could not relieve; but in nothing to proceed to the prejudice of the Law. And to that end his Lordſhip was made a Judge of the Law in ſome Caſes, and alſo a Judge by Conſcience, beſides the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule of Law in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caſes; for that being a Judge of the Law as well as others, his Lordſhip is with others to uphold the credit of the Law, and that moſt of all others; for that ſhe gave him
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152381:43"/>greater Authority than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and truſted him above all the reſt, in that ſhe tyed all the reſt to follow ſtrict Rules, and left him to rule by the Grace of God, and his own Conſcience, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve only the Equity, and not the ſtrict Rules thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherefore no man ought once to controll his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips judgement in any cauſe that he proceedeth in by his Abſolute power, but is with reverence to yeeld unto it, for as much as every one by the Rule of Charity, and of the eſtimation that we ought to have of them that God hath
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152381:43"/>ſubſtituted over us, is to judge the beſt, that is, that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath proceeded in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, according to his Conſcience, and the Director of a good Mans Conſcience is the will of God, which is the perfect rule of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, howſoever it ſeemeth to Man in his Wit or Judgement. Wherefore when his Lordſhip hath ſet down his judgement as God hath guided his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in any caſe, where he is Judge by Conſcience, though it differ from ſome other judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given either by himſelf, or any other good Man that ſat in his Seat, all men are bound to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152381:44"/>think, that the caſe differed in ſome circumſtance that they cannot ſee, or hath not underſtood it; Or that God in this caſe, according to his good Will, which is ſubject to no Rule but it ſelf, hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered this thus, and that ſo, and each being according to Gods good VVill, though dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in our Underſtanding the one from the other, both to be Righteous and Juſt Judgements, and are not to be diſliked, or diſobeyed of any.</p>
            <p n="12">12. But then was it doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome, whether his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Authority abſolute might
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152381:44"/>bind the great Men of the Land, <hi>viz.</hi> The Nobility as well as the mean Subjects? And the doubt roſe upon this, For that their Honours are not to be Arreſted by their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for any cauſe between Them and any Subject, by the Law of the Land, and the proceſſe out of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery is by Attachment of their Bodies, if they come not in upon a <hi>Sub-poena</hi> ſerved, and the execution of that Court is Impriſonment, untill the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will yield to obey the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and Order thereof, and by the <hi>Great Charter</hi> no Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ought to be Impriſoned,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152381:45"/>but by the Law of the Land. But that ſeemeth no cauſe, why the Order of the Lord Chancellor ſhould not bind them; for by the Law of the Land, if the Peers commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny contempt to the Crown, they are to be taken by their Bodies as other men. And Mr. <hi>Bracton, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. hath theſe words, <hi>Ea quae ſunt Juſtitiae &amp; Paci annexa ad nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum peirinent, niſi ad Coronam &amp; Dignitatem Regiam; eſt enim Coronae Regis facere Juſtitiam &amp; Judicium, &amp; tenere Pacem, &amp; illa à Corona ſeparari non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt.</hi> And what can be more near annexed to Juſtice, than
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152381:45"/>when a poor Man complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the chief Judgement Seat, that he ſhould have ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice according to Conſcience and Equity, without reſpect of perſons, and that his Might ſhould not overcome the poor Mans right; Therefore, when it is found, and Ordered for the poor Man, and his Right in Conſcience, and the great Man thereby appointed and Ordered, that he ſhall ceaſe his hard dealing with him, and he contemneth it, Muſt not that contempt needs be, <hi>Contra Coronam &amp; Dignitatem Regiam,</hi> ſeeing that Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot be ſeparated from
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152381:46"/>them? And then all Men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, That for any contempt againſt the Crown their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours may be arreſted and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned as well as any other Subjects.</p>
            <p>But in all theſe great Caſes, neither the Reader, nor any his Aſſociates took upon them to decide the Law, touching the Authorities aforeſaid, nor to give any certain Rules for them, but dealt only for Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to open the points, and leave the judgement to the Judges, (as the manner of that Exerciſe is) to determine what the Law is; And tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his Lordſhips Abſolute
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152381:46"/>Authority in this whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, they all, both the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and his Aſſociates, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord Chancellor himſelf, for every thing apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his Lordſhips Office; for that God hath not limited how farr, nor wherein, he ſhould go or deal, but guideth his Conſcience in every caſe that ſhall come before him, by his Grace, to do that which ſhall be good, juſt, and equall before God and Men, ſo farr as God ſhall direct him in that matter, for his own Glory, and the good, or puniſhment of the parties, according to his Good will.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:152381:47"/>
            <p n="13">13. But the laſt Note was this, That where every other Judge if he erreth in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is ſubject to a Writ of Error, to have his judgement examined by other Judges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, and ſo reverſed, and himſelf not to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if it be but error in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and if he erre of falſhood, then to be Fined, or puniſhed by the Lords in the <hi>Star Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and his falſe Action defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; Yet the Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> if he erre in his judgement, which he giveth according to his Conſcience, there is no Appeal to any but to God to reform it; for he is
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152381:47"/>the only Judge of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Man, and he only may condemn any for Error only in Conſcience, and he only may direct Conſcience into a better courſe, if Man erre therein; for every Man of his own Nature is ſubject therunto; and alſo for that in that reſpect, there is no Magiſtrate in <hi>England</hi> ſuperiour to him, for only the King or Queen is ſuperiour to him in Government, and they are not by the Law to diſtribute Juſtice themſelves, but are the ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents over all others, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate under God to appoint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to it, &amp; to ſee it done by them, and charge them with it, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152381:48"/>to maintain them therein.</p>
            <p>Thus eſcaping out of this Laborinth, they left it, as they found it, ſaving this doubt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, That his Lordſhips Authority and Office was ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Law, and remains a principal Member thereof, and that ſo of neceſsity, as without it the Law could not be juſt and equal to all in every Caſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152381:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
